<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on The Mindfield</title>
    <link>/posts/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on The Mindfield</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 11 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>From spreadsheet to print labels using python</title>
      <link>/posts/spreadsheet-to-print-labels-in-python/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/spreadsheet-to-print-labels-in-python/</guid>
      <description>As a plant biologist I routinely generate a lot of seed from the plants I grow and study. Pricipally at the moment this is the seed of Arabidopsis thaliana which is very small. To keep on top of things I catalogue all my seeds and keep a spreadsheet of all my seed.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An Emergent Theory of Art</title>
      <link>/posts/theory-of-art/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Oct 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/theory-of-art/</guid>
      <description>While recently listening to an episode of Radiolab 1 I was inspired to ruminate on my opinions about art and culture. One of their stories was about a system of pictorial symbols created to replace all languages with their inherent ambiguities and thus negate the possibility of misrepresentations and misunderstandings.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fired from the Cannon</title>
      <link>/posts/fired-from-the-cannon/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Oct 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/fired-from-the-cannon/</guid>
      <description>Note: that this was written before Disney brought Star Wars and the subsequent changes to what determines the cannon.
This post stems from a comment I made on an opinion piece by Michelle Smith on The Conversation 1 which dealt with how the Harry Potter series by J.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Life after the Synthetic Cell</title>
      <link>/posts/life-after-the-synthetic-cell/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Oct 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/life-after-the-synthetic-cell/</guid>
      <description>Note: This is a old piece from about 2012 but I still like it.
In mid-2010 headlines were created around the world when The J. Craig Venter Institute announced what they term the “assembly” of a self replicating cell with a chemically synthesized genome.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>