<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on The Mindfield</title>
    <link>/post/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on The Mindfield</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 12 Oct 2015 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>An Emergent Theory of Art</title>
      <link>/2015/10/12/an-emergent-theory-of-art/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Oct 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2015/10/12/an-emergent-theory-of-art/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!-- BLOGDOWN-HEAD --&gt;



&lt;!-- /BLOGDOWN-HEAD --&gt;

&lt;!-- BLOGDOWN-BODY-BEFORE --&gt;

&lt;!-- /BLOGDOWN-BODY-BEFORE --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While recently listening to an episode of Radiolab &lt;a href=&#34;#fn1&#34; class=&#34;footnoteRef&#34; id=&#34;fnref1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; I was inspired to ruminate on my opinions about art and culture. One of their stories was about a system of pictorial symbols created to replace all languages with their inherent ambiguities and thus negate the possibility of misrepresentations and misunderstandings. Needless to say, the idea did not take off. However it was successful as an intermediate form of communication when teaching literacy to children with cerebral palsy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What this Radiolab story (perhaps deliberately) did not address was that any language or writing system is inherently symbolic and therefore is inherently open to the problems bound up with interpretation. This is obviously a structuralist or post-structuralist position, the specifics of which I am not going to delve into. However it was interesting to note how in the story that despite the best efforts of the inventor of the symbolic system to literally represent reality, dialects and adaptations arose in the individual groups of children with cerebral palsy who used the symbols.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, something one of the interviewees said struck a chord with me. She described the use of the symbols as the distillation of essence of poetry, she thought that it forced you to think differently and re-examine, or be conscious, of the meanings of words and their juxtaposition to one another. Which led me to a very interesting question I have sporadically considered; What is the meaning of a word?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The way I see it I agree with Stephen Fry’s observation in his excellent blessay Don’t Mind Your Language… &lt;a href=&#34;#fn2&#34; class=&#34;footnoteRef&#34; id=&#34;fnref2&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; when discussing universal grammar:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A parent doesn’t teach language, much as they may think they do, they just occasionally spoon-feed a bit of vocabulary: moo-cow, baa-lamb, colours and so on, usually – you’ll never hear a parent say “and these are called ‘stairs’ or ‘to wash’ means ‘to clean with water’” – the child absorbs that kind of vocabulary without teaching.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here Fry is mainly talking about the structural underpinnings of communication however the point about vocabulary is illuminating. No one learns a language by reading the dictionary; rather the acquisition of words and their use occurs in an osmotic sort of way that you are largely unaware of. It is for this reason that it can often be difficult to precisely define words that you either read of speak in everyday life. For instance, what does the word “the” mean? Or “love” mean? (to be cliché).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The way I envisage it is that the learning of a word is a continual process and that our understanding of the definition of any particular word is contingent on our past experiences of the word being used and using the word ourselves. It is an amalgamation or composite of these past uses and just as importantly their context. This encompasses the content they concern, the words they are adjacent to in sentences and the sentences themselves that they appear in, amongst everything else. In a sense, every word (and instance of its use) is conceptually linked both forward and backward in time in our cultural perspective in terms of their relationship to other words and concepts. I imagine a complicated web like structure of resonances or allusions because it is really the interactions or links which are key in determining the meaning. This necessarily gives words a subjective, individual and fluid like quality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It should be noted that words can have multiple meanings; however these are not mutually exclusive and can overlap. For example, this memorable moment in J.R.R Tolkein’s The Hobbit:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Do you wish me a good morning, or mean that it is a good morning whether I want it or not; or that you feel good this morning; or that it is a morning to be good on?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“All of them at once,” said Bilbo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It could be assumed that all this subjectivity and multiple meanings would exponentially diversify the ecosystem of our cultural perspective. However this is not the case. Here it is useful to consider Information Theory and the redundancy of language.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A language such as English is inherently inefficient; the same could be said about any number of symbolic representations of the world. What this means it that the distribution of words, syllables, letters, symbols etc are not evenly nor randomly distributed throughout communication. Communication is inherently ordered. For instance, the occurrence of “u” after a “q” is very likely. The same can be said of phonemes and indeed words. This is what allows auto correction, compression, talking in a noisy environment and our ability to read abbreviations and misspellings. We do this by the triggering of resonances drawing on our past experience of a word to infer what someone will likely say next. We do this all the time and naturally this leads to us taking words for granted and not reconsidering their meanings anew with each use. Consequently, this restricts what words mean to us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not a bad thing; in fact it is essential as redundancy ensures that words mean something (a deliberately vague word) we all (sort of) agree on. Furthermore we can guess and learn new words based on their context. Language is a balance between innovation and conservation. This rings all sorts of evolutionary bells.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However this brings me back to seeing the use of the symbols as the distillation of essence of poetry and if we take symbolic systems to be the mediating factor in our understanding of the world it is applicable to all art and indeed culture. The novel placement of words in a poem (or motifs in a song or images in a painting etc.) forces the re-examination of the meanings of words by their juxtaposition to one another. This breaks our expectations of redundancy to understand the world in an unexpected or alternative way. Furthermore it forces us to understand how we understand. In a sense the meaning of an artwork is an emergent property of the connections between its constituent parts and not a single thing in and of itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is an interesting thought to consider that in cultural evolution the unit of culture may be in the connections or collections of resonances. I consider this a Systems Culture perspective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Such a perspective has interesting ramifications about how we understand memories. There is a cool debate over whether memories are like video being replayed or are in fact recreated in the mind with each remembrance and that each remembrance is in turn influenced by previous remembrances. The latter option supports the emergent theory of art and is in turn supported by our understanding of empathy, and visualisation &lt;a href=&#34;#fn3&#34; class=&#34;footnoteRef&#34; id=&#34;fnref3&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Another angle is the interesting collision between individual and collective memory and how the overlap between the two can be part of the artwork itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An emergent theory of art raises all sorts of interesting questions about the relationship of the artwork and the world (which it is both commenting upon and part of), authorial intention and the role of the reader or perceiver of the artwork because it is of course subjective and context specific. An exciting consequence of this is how an artwork can have different meanings for different people and even different meanings for the same person at different moments in time. Yet curiously there are still things which can be said about it. I believe that this is what lies behind the common themes that are perceived in an authors work over their lifetime.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What can be said about art brings me to another conception of art, that it is the expression of the individual human experience to others. That which is generally considered inexpressible. This view often presupposes a distinction between thought and language, our experience of reality and expression but this is not necessarily the case and not a debate I wish to pursue here. In contrast, an emergent theory of art differs from such a view in that rather than an expression of the individual human experience, it is rather a function of it. I guess how big a difference that is a matter of personal taste and opinion of agency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To conclude I would like to stress that this is just a theory of art, one of many, and by definition the result of my cultural resonances. The balance between innovation and conservation of language rests upon its ambiguities and misrepresentations are the price we pay in the unwieldy phenomena of emergence. I don’t assume that this is an original idea, some linguist somewhere must have thought of it but I don’t know who so I’ll credit it to the cultural ether.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn1&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.radiolab.org/2012/dec/17/&#34;&gt;Radiolab episode Season 11(3)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn2&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.stephenfry.com/2008/11/04/dont-mind-your-language%E2%80%A6/&#34;&gt;Steven Fry Blessay&lt;/a&gt; and there is an audio version &lt;a href=&#34;https://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/stephen-frys-podgrams-audio/id274722189&#34;&gt; here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref2&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn3&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;I think I heard about this in Frank Rose’s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.artofimmersion.com/&#34;&gt;The Art of Immersion&lt;/a&gt; which to me highlights how narrative is the most important element of how we understand the world. Narrative, the causal connection of disparate events, is of course analogous to cultural emergence. This is his historiographic in its piecemeal but dynamic approach.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref3&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fired from the Cannon</title>
      <link>/2015/10/12/fired-from-the-cannon/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Oct 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2015/10/12/fired-from-the-cannon/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!-- BLOGDOWN-HEAD --&gt;



&lt;!-- /BLOGDOWN-HEAD --&gt;

&lt;!-- BLOGDOWN-BODY-BEFORE --&gt;

&lt;!-- /BLOGDOWN-BODY-BEFORE --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post stems from a comment I made on an opinion piece by Michelle Smith on The Conversation &lt;a href=&#34;#fn1&#34; class=&#34;footnoteRef&#34; id=&#34;fnref1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; which dealt with how the Harry Potter series by J. K. Rowling should be interpreted in the light of statements by J. K. Rowling after publication. This was deemed especially pertinent when it concerned controversial issues such as homosexuality. Some commenters consider it to be jumping on a progressive bandwagon and/or attempting to retain influence over the text. In general Smith sided with the popular and standard “Death of the Author” argument which in a post-strucualist manner advocates a plurality of interpretations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However in reading the article I was prodded onto a line of thinking I have often mulled over, that is that the “Death of the Author” argument to my mind does not fit well with a text which is a serial work. Specifically, the way J. K. Rowling has continued to comment on her works raises interesting questions about what is “the text” of Harry Potter. Is it just the seven novels? if so, why? or are they individual texts?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would argue that most readers of the Harry Potter books would not contest the assertion that latter books influence the interpretation of the earlier books when assessed retrospectively. To read the first two books and surmise that the story of Harry Potter ends there is of course possible. However this is emphatically not how the vast majority of readers have interacted with the books over the past 17 years. Rather you read them all with the books themselves having a definite continuous sequence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this case “the text” is considered the whole of the series. This is reinforced by the flashbacks (or “memories in the pensive”) in the final books which prompt reassessments of the actions and motivations of key characters such as Dumbledore and Snape.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So if installments like books 6 and 7 which J. K. Rowling wrote after the earlier works can count towards the entirety of the text why not other information she later introduces through other mediums? Why are the novels privileged over tweets and her responses in interviews? Of course one could choose to disregard these later outputs, but why do they carry less weight than a novel? Why should J. K. Rowlings intentions be so much more authoritative when she writes them down and sells them from a store?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I guess what I’m saying is that whenever I see a discussion about “The Death of the Author” it always seems to treat “the text” as a stand alone easily defined whole. When in reality this is increasingly rarely the case. A singular text does not allow for stories presented in series in an age where aspects of a story can be presented in a cross media fashion through channels such as film, video games, visual art, and words on a page among many others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is worth remembering that post-structualists like Barthes and Foucault by and large wrote within and are interpreted by a discipline concerned with mostly “traditional” texts such as stand alone novels and poetry. A better understanding of Harry Potter could be gained by supplementing such analysis with a comparison to other cross-media texts. For example, Star Wars. In communities interested in such cross-media texts the question of authorial authority is re-framed as “canonicity” or “continuity”. Ignoring the religious implications it is worth noting that this inherently implies a broader more fluid notion of a text with potentially multiple authors or contributors and multiple levels of canonicity which increase in order of precedence. Thus for one “reader” there is not one interpretation of the text, let alone the author. Rather it requires accepted fictional logic which maintains the suspension of disbelief created by the narrative.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In today’s fractured media environment it is intriguing to consider the possibility that texts like Harry Potter and the relationships between authors and their audiences cannot be defined as neatly as a classic stand alone novel. Thus while having written the Harry Potter novels forced J. K. Rowling to relinquish complete influence of intention upon publication, this does not mean she has lost all influence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the Star Wars community the most authoritative level of canonicity is termed G-canon. These G-canon sources override any other conflict in the interpretation of the Star Wars universe. G-cannon stands for George Lucas Canon and include anything he has to say on the subject &lt;a href=&#34;#fn2&#34; class=&#34;footnoteRef&#34; id=&#34;fnref2&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. While ultimate interpretation rests with audiences and readers I would not be surprised if fans of Harry Potter confer J.K. Rowling with a similar status.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn1&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://theconversation.com/the-death-of-j-k-rowling-why-it-doesnt-matter-what-she-has-to-say-about-harry-potter-35762&#34;&gt;The ‘death’ of J. K. Rowling: Why it doesn’t matter what she has to say about Harry Potter by Michelle Smith &lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn2&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Star_Wars_canon&#34;&gt;Overview of Star Wars canon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref2&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Life after the Synthetic Cell</title>
      <link>/2015/10/12/life-after-the-synthetic-cell/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Oct 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2015/10/12/life-after-the-synthetic-cell/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!-- BLOGDOWN-HEAD --&gt;



&lt;!-- /BLOGDOWN-HEAD --&gt;

&lt;!-- BLOGDOWN-BODY-BEFORE --&gt;

&lt;!-- /BLOGDOWN-BODY-BEFORE --&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note: This is a old piece from about 2012 but I still like it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In mid-2010 headlines were created around the world when The J. Craig Venter Institute announced what they term the “assembly” of a self replicating cell with a chemically synthesized genome. This was achieved by the &lt;em&gt;in vitro&lt;/em&gt; reproduction of the 1.08 megabase genome of &lt;em&gt;Mycoplasma mycoides&lt;/em&gt;, a ruminant parasite and the subsequent transplantation into a &lt;em&gt;M. capricolum&lt;/em&gt; cell with its genome removed. In addition the authors added some “watermarks” in the form of their names, an email address and some pertinent quotes translated into amino acids to prove that they had done it &lt;a href=&#34;#fn1&#34; class=&#34;footnoteRef&#34; id=&#34;fnref1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.The production of a self replicating cell with a chemically synthesized genome is a flagship paper in what has become the exciting field of synthetic biology, here I discuss where science is focusing next.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The principle aims of synthetic biology are threefold. Firstly, to determine the basis of life, or more specifically, the core components required for a (proto-)organism to be classified as alive. Hence the Richard Feynman quote “What I cannot build, I cannot understand” in the “wartermarks” of the synthetic cell is very appropriate. The current theoretical minimum is approximated at 100-151 genes &lt;a href=&#34;#fn2&#34; class=&#34;footnoteRef&#34; id=&#34;fnref2&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Mycoplasma&lt;/em&gt; was selected as a model organism to study this question because it has the smallest genome of any organism that can be cultured in the lab (organisms with smaller genomes do exist, but are often endosymbionts and/or cannot be cultured). Previous work has found &lt;em&gt;M. genitalium&lt;/em&gt; has a minimal genome of 382 essential genes &lt;a href=&#34;#fn3&#34; class=&#34;footnoteRef&#34; id=&#34;fnref3&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, albeit in a lab situation. No doubt as the environment changes different (and larger) sets of genes become essential.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In light of this work, it was very exciting when in July of this year researchers at Stanford University, in collaboration with The J. Craig Venter Institute, announced their whole-cell computational model of &lt;em&gt;M. genitalium&lt;/em&gt; incorporating a diverse range of experimental datasets. This “first draft” of the model encompasses the full life cycle of the cell and takes the full 525 genes in the genome as well as all of the organism’s molecular components and known interactions in 28 integrated sub-models &lt;a href=&#34;#fn4&#34; class=&#34;footnoteRef&#34; id=&#34;fnref4&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Where the production of a cell with a chemically synthesised genome required the digitisation of the genome, the digitisation of the entire cell is an impressive technical achievement, however it also has important practical applications. These centre on the models phenotypic predictions given the genotype. For example, when analysing the behaviour of DNA-binding proteins the model predicts that 50% of the bacterial chromosome interacts with at least one protein in the first six minutes, 90% in the first 20 minutes and 90% of genes being expressed in the first 143 minutes &lt;a href=&#34;#fn5&#34; class=&#34;footnoteRef&#34; id=&#34;fnref5&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. This type of analysis at a holistic cell wide level and scale allows the identification of emergent phenomena. In &lt;em&gt;M. genitalium&lt;/em&gt; it appears that dNTP metabolism may impose restrictions on the duration of the cell cycle not previously identified &lt;a href=&#34;#fn6&#34; class=&#34;footnoteRef&#34; id=&#34;fnref6&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;6&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given the 525 genes, the whole-cell computational model of &lt;em&gt;M. genitalium&lt;/em&gt; seems ideally placed to assess the question of a minimal genome. Through simulated gene disruptions the model can delve into why a gene product is needed in the cell system giving new insights. It suggests that there are 284 essential genes which agrees with the experimental results with 79% accuracy &lt;a href=&#34;#fn7&#34; class=&#34;footnoteRef&#34; id=&#34;fnref7&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;7&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. This shortfall is actually informative as incorrect predictions allow the targeted identification of pathways and interactions not currently known or understood. Thus indicating the gaps in scientific knowledge and where experimental work should focus next.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This leads on to the second aim of synthetic biology, the illumination of gene function by the expression in novel contexts. This is already a mainstay of contemporary biotechnology however it is limited to a few genes at a time and it is anticipated that the developing techniques of synthetic biology will accelerate this process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The logical next step in the synthetic biology process is naturally larger and more complex systems, which is relevant to the third aim of synthetic biology, practical biological engineering applications. The next cells to be produced with (at least partially) chemically synthesised genomes will likely be first &lt;em&gt;E. coli&lt;/em&gt; and then eukaryotes, most probably single-celled algae with the intention of developing algae biofuels &lt;a href=&#34;#fn8&#34; class=&#34;footnoteRef&#34; id=&#34;fnref8&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;8&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. In fact, Synthetic Genomics Inc., Craig Venter’s private company for synthetic biology purchased 81 acres of southern California in May of this year with the explicit intention of developing engineered strains of algae, funded by ExxonMobil and BP among others &lt;a href=&#34;#fn9&#34; class=&#34;footnoteRef&#34; id=&#34;fnref9&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;9&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, synthetic biology has applications beyond biofuels, although this is definitely one of the most promising areas. Hydrocarbon recovery, water purification, agricultural improvement, hydrogen production, vaccine development, pharmaceutical production, whole cell biosensors and targeted therapies are all ideas which have been floated &lt;a href=&#34;#fn10&#34; class=&#34;footnoteRef&#34; id=&#34;fnref10&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;10&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is much work being carried out to achieve these goals most of which are trying to apply classical engineering concepts to these complex systems, principally “modularity, component testing, standards, interfaces, libraries of parts and computer-aided design” &lt;a href=&#34;#fn11&#34; class=&#34;footnoteRef&#34; id=&#34;fnref11&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;11&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Naturally this centres around the production of Boolean-like logic structures to construct circuits from modules like a regular electrical circuit or software program. These include switches and oscillators and many researchers have the aim of creating an inventory of wetware components that can be substituted in or out as needed &lt;a href=&#34;#fn12&#34; class=&#34;footnoteRef&#34; id=&#34;fnref12&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;12&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;sup&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;#fn13&#34; class=&#34;footnoteRef&#34; id=&#34;fnref13&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;13&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. The idea of developing specialized programming languages for biological systems to abstractly design systems is a novel and innovative idea &lt;a href=&#34;#fn14&#34; class=&#34;footnoteRef&#34; id=&#34;fnref14&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;14&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However any of this work must take into consideration the range of factors inherent in biological systems such as noise, life-cycle, interactions, feedback mechanisms, component matching, mutations, variations in environmental conditions and cellular context to name a few &lt;a href=&#34;#fn15&#34; class=&#34;footnoteRef&#34; id=&#34;fnref15&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;15&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. An interesting decision that must be made is whether, in order to function in the real world, these synthetic organisms should have their function be rigidly dictated by their design or should a level of dynamism be built in? Given that biological systems are dynamic the answers are not straightforward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Breaking a living cell down into its constituent parts is not the approach to synthetic biology and other groups of researchers are taking some different approaches. Broadly speaking these can be classified as “bottom up” approaches as opposed to “top down” and can be thought of as grouping into three general categories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first approach comes from the research programs studying the origin of life on Earth. Simply put, labs such as that of Jack Szostak (2009 Nobel Laureate) aim to reproduce the processes that resulted in the shift from chemical evolution to biological evolution on the early Earth by investigating replicating vesicles, RNA and protein selection &lt;a href=&#34;#fn16&#34; class=&#34;footnoteRef&#34; id=&#34;fnref16&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;16&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. The idea of defining life may not help in making clear the origin of life &lt;a href=&#34;#fn17&#34; class=&#34;footnoteRef&#34; id=&#34;fnref17&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;17&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; but understanding the origin of life may help understanding the minimal requirements for life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A similar but subtlety different approach is the construction of life from scratch, with the explicit aim of developing a global understanding of cellular life by the artificial construction of a cell from its basic structural elements. These include both genetic and non-genetic processes. In a sense, this is the complementary approach to the creation of a cell with a chemically synthesized genome in that it is concerned with the creation of cellular “hardware” not “software.” After all while the physical structure of a cell is regulated by its genetic material, the cell with a chemically synthesized genome still initially required existing cellular machinery. One prominent aspect of this approach’s practitioners is concerned with the construction of artificial organelles (e.g. ribosomes).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An excellent example of this approach is the artificial cell project which aims to construct a minimal cell and takes John Von Neumann’s theoretical work on replicating automata to study self-reproducing systems. To date, the project has achieved transient simple gene expression in synthetic vesicles &lt;a href=&#34;#fn18&#34; class=&#34;footnoteRef&#34; id=&#34;fnref18&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;18&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. It would be interesting to see whether Stephen Wolfram’s work on cellular automata has anything to contribute to this line of investigation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The third category of “bottom up” synthetic biology is much more undefined. It asks why should cells be the smallest basic unit of life and explores a much broader understanding of what life can be &lt;a href=&#34;#fn19&#34; class=&#34;footnoteRef&#34; id=&#34;fnref19&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;19&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. It is the study of self-organizing processes in natural and human made systems. The majority of this field is theoretical and consists of mathematical speculation and/or computer simulations. This area has a large overlap with astrobiology (or xenobiology to use a better term) &lt;a href=&#34;#fn20&#34; class=&#34;footnoteRef&#34; id=&#34;fnref20&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;20&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Synthetic biology is obviously an area where ethical and security risks need to be at the forefront of the discussion &lt;a href=&#34;#fn21&#34; class=&#34;footnoteRef&#34; id=&#34;fnref21&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;21&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;sup&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;#fn22&#34; class=&#34;footnoteRef&#34; id=&#34;fnref22&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;22&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, however each case will need to be considered on a case by case basis. It is difficult to make general statements. It is inevitable that there will be claims of “playing god,” an interesting claim to unpack. However most observers consider that “few, if any, new ethical issues are raised” &lt;a href=&#34;#fn23&#34; class=&#34;footnoteRef&#34; id=&#34;fnref23&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;23&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Nevertheless, the prominence in the public eye provides a good opportunity to engage and communicate with the public which can only be a good thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an aside, it is observe that the phrase “playing god” is much more commonly used by non-religious critics of biotechnology than religious groups &lt;a href=&#34;#fn24&#34; class=&#34;footnoteRef&#34; id=&#34;fnref24&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;24&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and that the God of “playing God” may not actually be the God of the Bible, but rather “deified nature” &lt;a href=&#34;#fn25&#34; class=&#34;footnoteRef&#34; id=&#34;fnref25&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;25&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Synthetic biology therefore has profound philosophical implications to be explored as well with regards to our relationship to the natural world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are many other topics that the field of synthetic biology has yet to tackle. Chief among these are the issues surrounding multi-cellularity and the phenomena of emergence. Synthetic biology of higher levels of biological organization have not been discussed, such as synthetic ecosystems, however the applicable fields (e.g. invasion ecology) are significantly advanced and too board to be summarized here. Lastly, there are many small novel projects which only time will tell what impact they will have, one of particular note is intracellular data storage which uses a “rewritable recombinase addressable data module” to use the genetic code as a sort of binary data storage &lt;a href=&#34;#fn26&#34; class=&#34;footnoteRef&#34; id=&#34;fnref26&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;26&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Nevertheless the ultimate goal of synthetic biology is the &lt;em&gt;de novo&lt;/em&gt; scripting of genetic code. When this is achieved the result will be very exciting to see.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn1&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Gibson et al. (2010). &lt;i&gt;Science&lt;/i&gt;. doi:&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencemag.org/content/329/5987/52&#34;&gt;10.1126/science.1190719&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn2&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Purnick and Weiss. (2009). &lt;i&gt;Nature Reviews Molecular Cell Biology&lt;/i&gt;. doi:&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nature.com/nrm/journal/v10/n6/full/nrm2698.html&#34;&gt;10.1038/nrm2698&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref2&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn3&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Glass et al. (2006). &lt;i&gt;PNAS&lt;/i&gt;. doi:&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pnas.org/content/103/2/425&#34;&gt;10.1073/pnas.0510013103&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref3&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn4&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Karr et al. (2012). &lt;i&gt;Cell&lt;/i&gt;. doi:&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cell.com/abstract/S0092-8674%2812%2900776-3&#34;&gt;10.1016/j.cell.2012.05.044&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref4&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn5&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Karr et al. (2012). &lt;i&gt;Cell&lt;/i&gt;. doi:&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cell.com/abstract/S0092-8674%2812%2900776-3&#34;&gt;10.1016/j.cell.2012.05.044&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref5&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn6&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Karr et al. (2012). &lt;i&gt;Cell&lt;/i&gt;. doi:&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cell.com/abstract/S0092-8674%2812%2900776-3&#34;&gt;10.1016/j.cell.2012.05.044&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref6&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn7&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Karr et al. (2012). &lt;i&gt;Cell&lt;/i&gt;. doi:&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cell.com/abstract/S0092-8674%2812%2900776-3&#34;&gt;10.1016/j.cell.2012.05.044&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref7&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn8&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Actually with hindsight see Annaluru et al. (2014). &lt;i&gt;Science&lt;/i&gt;. doi:&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sciencemag.org/content/344/6179/55&#34;&gt;10.1126/science.1249252&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref8&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn9&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.syntheticgenomics.com/240512.html&#34;&gt;Synthetic Genomics Inc. Press Release 24/5/2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref9&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn10&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Khalil and Collins. (2010). &lt;i&gt;Nature Reviews Genetics&lt;/i&gt;. doi:&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nature.com/nrg/journal/v11/n5/full/nrg2775.html&#34;&gt;10.1038/nrg2775&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref10&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn11&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Purnick and Weiss. (2009). &lt;i&gt;Nature Reviews Molecular Cell Biology&lt;/i&gt;. doi:&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nature.com/nrm/journal/v10/n6/full/nrm2698.html&#34;&gt;10.1038/nrm2698&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref11&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn12&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Purnick and Weiss. (2009). &lt;i&gt;Nature Reviews Molecular Cell Biology&lt;/i&gt;. doi:&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nature.com/nrm/journal/v10/n6/full/nrm2698.html&#34;&gt;10.1038/nrm2698&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref12&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn13&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Khalil and Collins. (2010). &lt;i&gt;Nature Reviews Genetics&lt;/i&gt;. doi:&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nature.com/nrg/journal/v11/n5/full/nrg2775.html&#34;&gt;10.1038/nrg2775&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref13&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn14&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Purnick and Weiss. (2009). &lt;i&gt;Nature Reviews Molecular Cell Biology&lt;/i&gt;. doi:&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nature.com/nrm/journal/v10/n6/full/nrm2698.html&#34;&gt;10.1038/nrm2698&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref14&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn15&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Purnick and Weiss. (2009). &lt;i&gt;Nature Reviews Molecular Cell Biology&lt;/i&gt;. doi:&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nature.com/nrm/journal/v10/n6/full/nrm2698.html&#34;&gt;10.1038/nrm2698&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref15&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn16&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Schrum, Zhu and Szostak. (2010). &lt;i&gt;Cold Spring Harbor Perspectives in Biology&lt;/i&gt;. doi:&lt;a href=&#34;http://cshperspectives.cshlp.org/content/2/9/a002212&#34;&gt;10.1101/cshperspect.a002212&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref16&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn17&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Szostak. (2012). &lt;i&gt;Journal of Biomolecular Structure and Dynamics&lt;/i&gt;. doi:&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.1080/073911012010524998&#34;&gt;10.1080/073911012010524998&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref17&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn18&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Noireaux, Maeda and Libchaber. (2010). &lt;i&gt;PNAS&lt;/i&gt;. doi:&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pnas.org/content/108/9/3473&#34;&gt; 10.1073/pnas.1017075108&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref18&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn19&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Tirard, Morange and Lazcano. (2010). &lt;i&gt;Astrobiology&lt;/i&gt;. doi:&lt;a href=&#34;http://online.liebertpub.com/doi/abs/10.1089/ast.2010.0535&#34;&gt;10.1089/ast.2010.0535&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref19&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn20&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Cohen, and Stewart. (2001). &lt;i&gt;Nature&lt;/i&gt;. doi:&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nature.com/nature/journal/v409/n6823/full/4091119a0.html&#34;&gt;10.1038/35059248&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref20&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn21&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Gibson et al. (2010). &lt;i&gt;Science&lt;/i&gt;. doi:&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencemag.org/content/329/5987/52&#34;&gt;10.1126/science.1190719&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref21&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn22&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Khalil and Collins. (2010). &lt;i&gt;Nature Reviews Genetics&lt;/i&gt;. doi:&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nature.com/nrg/journal/v11/n5/full/nrg2775.html&#34;&gt;10.1038/nrg2775&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref22&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn23&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Cho and Relman. (2010). &lt;i&gt;Science&lt;/i&gt;. doi:&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencemag.org/content/329/5987/38&#34;&gt;10.1126/science.1193749&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref23&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn24&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Link. (2013). &lt;i&gt;Science and Engineering Ethics&lt;/i&gt;. doi:&lt;a href=&#34;http://link.springer.com/article/10.1007%2Fs11948-012-9353-z&#34;&gt;10.1007/s11948-012-9353-z&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref24&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn25&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;van den Belt. (2009). &lt;i&gt;NanoEthics&lt;/i&gt;. doi:&lt;a href=&#34;http://link.springer.com/article/10.1007%2Fs11569-009-0079-6&#34;&gt;10.1007/s11569-009-0079-6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref25&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn26&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Bonnet, Subsoontorn and Endy. (2012). &lt;i&gt;PNAS&lt;/i&gt;. doi:&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pnas.org/content/109/23/8884&#34;&gt;10.1073/pnas.1202344109 &lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref26&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>